Guide to the Shane Lavalette photographs, 2010-2011 RL.11368
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Shane Lavalette photographs
2010-2011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lavalette, Shane, 1987-
RL.11368
1.5 Linear Feet 1 flat box 25 prints 20x24 inches
The 25 photographs in this collection belong to a body of work entitled One Sun, One Shadow, which was commissioned by the High Museum of Art in Atlanta for the 2012 exhibition Picturing the South. They were all taken in the American South from 2010 to 2011, and explore Lavalette's connection to the South through landscapes, people, and music traditions. Though the majority of the 20x24 inch inkjet prints are in color, there are also five black-and-white prints. Titles for each print were assigned by the photographer. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Content Description
The 25 photographs in this collection belong to a body of work entitled One Sun, One Shadow, which was commissioned by the High Museum of Art in Atlanta for the 2012 exhibition Picturing the South. They were all taken in the American South from 2010 to 2011, and explore Lavalette's connection to the South through landscapes, people, and music traditions. Most were taken outdoors, but there are a few interior shots.
Though the majority of the 20x24 inch inkjet prints are in color, there are also five black-and-white prints. Titles for each print were created by the photographer.
In addition to Lavalette's photographic body of work, the Rubenstein Library also holds copies of the companion photo book, One Sun, One Shadow. The images are also available to view through the photographer's website.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Biographical Note
Shane Lavalette (b. 1987, Burlington, VT) is an American photographer, the founding publisher/editor of Lavalette, an independent press, and the director of Light Work, a non-profit organization supporting photographers and artists in related media. He holds a BFA from Tufts University in partnership with The School of the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston.
Lavalette's photographs have been shown widely, including exhibitions at the High Museum of Art, Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University, Aperture Gallery, Montserrat College of Art, The Carpenter Center for Visual Arts at Harvard University, The Center for Photography at Woodstock, The Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, and Musée de l'Elysée, Paris, in addition to works held in private and public collections. In 2016, a solo exhibition of the photographs in this collection, One Sun, One Shadow was presented at Robert Morat Galerie in Hamburg, Germany.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Images may only be used for educational, non-commercial purposes.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Shane Lavalette photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2016.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Inkjet prints are particularly vulnerable to moisture and other substances. Please handle print with gloves and refrain from touching the image surface.
Related Materials
One Sun, One Shadow (photo book)
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
Documentary Photography -- Southern States; Photographers -- New York (State); Southern States -- Photographs; Black-and-white photographs; Color photographs; Digital prints; Inkjet prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
- One Sun, One Shadow, 2010-2011; 25 prints 1 box Inkjet prints 20x24 inches
  Scope and Contents
  Prints are arranged in the original order as assigned by the photographer. Each one has the print number, title, and date written on the back.
  - Kaylyn swinging, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Hanging tree, 2011 (Box 1)
  - Spirit bottles, 2011 (Box 1)
  - Tommy's bed, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Praying hands, 2011 (Box 1)
  - Birds in flight, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Tracks, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Ground zero, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Rev. Dennis's Bible Castle to God, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Looking at the sun, 2011 (Box 1)
  - White bread, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Storm, 2010 (Box 1)
  - We're all gonna die, 2011 (Box 1)
  - Montre, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Will with banjo, 2011 (Box 1)
  - Athens morning, 2011 (Box 1)
  - Natural burn, 2011 (Box 1)
  - Natural burn (II), 2011 (Box 1)
  - Spit in the swamp, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Ashley at Ben Burton, 2011 (Box 1)
  - Chattanooga, 2011 (Box 1)
  - Binoculars, 2011 (Box 1)
  - Church, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Sun Studios, 2010 (Box 1)
  - Secret Squirrel, 2011 (Box 1)